A Guide to the Amelia County (Va.) Records, 1736-1914, undated
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Amelia County (Va.) Records, 1736-1914, undated
The Library of Virginia
1043094-1145807
43 boxes--41 found at State Records Center--Archives Annex, Library of Virginia and 2 (1154780 and 1160450 ) found at Library of Virginia.
Amelia County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in a variety of ways. One item, accession 19925, was transferred from a historical society, One item, accession 21384. was purchased. One item, accession 25606, was transferred from an individual. Various items, accession numbers 20444. 20920, 20922, 20923, 20924, 20926, 20952 and 22555, were lent from Amelia County Circuit Court for copying. The rest of the items came in a transfer of court records from Amelia County under the accession numbers 37990, 37993, 37995, 40724, 41507, 43189. Information on accession number 33213 is unknown.
Historical Information
Amelia County was named for Amelia Sophia Eleanora, daughter of King George II. The county was formed from Prince George and Brunswick counties by an act passed in 1734. The act was to take effect on 25 March 1735. The county court first met on 9 May 1735.
Scope and Content
Amelia County (Va.) Records, 1736-1914, undated, consist of the following series: Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Election Records, Court Records (subfield series include Docket Book, Order, Judgments, Criminal Records, and Clerks' Records), Marriage Records and Vital Statistics, Tax and Fiscal Records, Public Buildings and Grounds Records, Fiduciary Records, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Road and Bridge Records, Wills, Justice of the Peace Records, Land Records, School Records, Organization Records, County Administrative Records (subfield series include Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, Treasurers' Records, Commissioner of the Revenue Records and Overseers of the Poor Records), Business Records and Health and Medical Records.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Amelia County Records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm" found on the Library of Virginia's web site.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Amelia County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
Public records--Virginia--Amelia County.
Geographical Names:
Amelia County (Va.)--History.
Genre and Form Terms:
Local government records--Virginia--Amelia County.
Contents List
- OVERSIZED Records, 1736-1805
  Bonds/Commissions/Oaths: Commissions to Justices of the Peace, 1736, 1777 (Accession number 20444), Oaths of Allegiance, 1777 - Negative photostat (Accession number 20924); Election Records: Poll taken for Captain Edmund Booker at an election of Burgesses, 20 July 1758 - Negative photostat (Accession number 20922), Poll for Burgesses, 6 December 1768 - Negative photostat (Accession number 20923); Court Records: Docket Book, 1757-1758 (Accession number 21384); Marriage Records and Vital Statistics: Marriage Bonds and Minister Returns, 1744-1785 (Accession number 20920); Tax and Fiscal Records: Personal Property Tax Lists, 1805 (Accession number 25606); Public Buildings and Grounds Records: Petition for re-location of the courthouse (1 item; copy) Negative photostat (Accession number 20952.)
- OVERSIZED Records, 1739, 1777, 1787
  Copy of loose order dated 1739 found in Amelia County Minute Book 1744-1746; Print, dated May 15, 1777, of a commission appointing Justices of the Peace in Amelia County--Accession number 20926; Bond, dated Dec. 10, 1787, of Thomas Jordan and Richard Cross to Richard Bland, Gdn of Ann Bland--Accession number 19925.
- Records, 1807-1914
  Court Records: Summons, Notices; Election Records; Fiduciary Records; Clerk's Records (Correspondence, clerk's fees, etc.)
- Records, 1825-1903
  Election Records: Voter Registration Books for Giles, Jackson, and Leigh Districts, 1903; Tax and Fiscal Records: County Levies of poor rates, 1864, Tax books - land and personal property, 1825-1878; Marriage Records and Vital Statistics: List of births and deaths, 1874, Register sheets for births, deaths, and marriages, 1853-1864.
- Records, 1800-1809
  Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills. Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1810-1816
  Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Court Records:Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Justice of the Peace Records, Land Records, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507. Box also contains Bonds/Commissions/Oaths folder, 1810-1814, with the following Accession numbers 37990, 37993, 37995.
- Records, 1817-1822
  Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Justice of the Peace Records, Land Records, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1823-1827
  Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Justice of the Peace Records, Land Records, Marriage Records and Vital Statistics, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Road and Bridge Records, School Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1828-1832
  Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Justice of the Peace Records, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, Road and Bridge Records, School Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1833-1838
  Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Election Records, Fiduciary Records, Justice of the Peace Records, Marriage Records and Vital Statistics, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1839-1846
  Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Justice of the Peace Records, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Road and Bridge Records, School Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1847-1853
  Court Records: Criminal Records, Election Records, Fiduciary Records, Justice of the Peace Records, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1854-1856
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Election Records, Fiduciary Records, Justice of the Peace Records, Land Records, Miscellaneous Records, Road and Bridge Records, Tax amd Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1857-1859
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Election Records, Fiduciary Records, Justice of the Peace Records, Land Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1860-1863
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Election Records, Fiduciary Records, Justice of the Peace Records, Land Records, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1864-1867
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Justice of the Peace Records, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1868-1869
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1870-1871
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Election Records, Fiduciary Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1872-1873
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Land Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1874-1876
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Marriage Records and Vital Statistics, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1877-1878
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Land Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1879-1880
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Election Records, Fiduciary Records, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1881-1882
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Business Records/ Corporations/ Partnerships, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Land Records, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1883-1884
- Records, 1885
- Records, 1886
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Military and Pension Records, Organization Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1887-1888
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Business Records/ Corporations/ Partnerships, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road snd Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1889-1891
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1892-1893
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Election Records, Fiduciary Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Accession number 41507. Box also contains Court Records: Criminal Records (1893) from Accession number 37995.
- Records, 1894-1895
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Business Records/Corporations/Partnerships, Court Records: Criminal Records, Election Records, Fiduciary Records, Land Records, Marriage Records and Vital Statistics, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1896-1898
- Records, 1899-1900
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Miscellaneous Records, Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1901-1903
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Election Records, Fiduciary Records, Land Records, Marriage Records and Vital Statistics, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1904-1906
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Justice of the Peace Records, Land Records, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1907-1910
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Election Records, Fiduciary Records, Land Records, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, Road and Bridge Records, School Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1911-1913
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, Court Records: Criminal Records, Fiduciary Records, Land Records, Marriage Records and Vital Statistics, Military and Pension Records, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, School Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Wills, Accession number 41507.
- Records, 1913
  Court Records: Criminal Records, Land Records, Marriage Records and Vital Statistics, Miscellaneous Records, Organization Records, Accession number 41507.
- OVERSIZED Records, 1793-1913
  Court Records: Criminal Records, 1 document (1810), 3 documents (1813), 1 document (1901); Fiduciary Records, 1 plat, estate division (1848); Court Records, letter of attorney (1815); Marriage Records and Vital Statististics, 3 marriage licenses (1913); Tax and Fiscal Records, list of ordinary keepers, 1 document (1808-1811); Road and Bridge Records, l document, List of Road Surveyors (1793-1811) County Administrative Records: Board of Supervisors Records: Road and Bridge Records, 1 plat (1874), 1 document--plans and specs (1890); 1 contract, blueprint and spec sheet (1900), 1 contract--plans and specs (1901), Accession number 41507.
- OVERSIZED Records, 1850-1893
  Court Records: Criminal Records, documents and exhibits (1893); Fiduciary Records, estate division, 1 plat (1850); Tax and Fiscal Records, 1 personal property tax book (1850), 1 list of county claims and 1 list of delinquent lands (1859); 1 list of delinquent lands (1861); 3 lists of delinquent land tax (1862); Insolvent Capitation and Personal Property Tax Lists (1871)--8 sheets, 1872--8 sheets, 1873--9 sheets, County Administrative Records: Treasurers' Records, 1885 (6 sheets), 1886 (4 sheets), 1889 (5 sheets), 1890 (4 sheets), Accession number 41507.
- OVERSIZED Records, 1741-1911
  Bonds/ Commissions/ Oaths, 1741 (1 document from Accession number 43189--Sheriff's Appointment)-; Fiduciary Records: Estate Divisions, 1855 (1 plat and 1 order), 1863 (1 plat and 2 documents), 1868 (2 plats), 1876 (1 plat), 1878 (1 plat); Fiduciary Records, 1868 (1 plat)--Estate of John G. Jefferson re: estate division; Marriage Records and Vital Statistics: Register of Births and Deaths, 1892 (5 sheets); Military and Pension Records: 1911 (1 document); Road and Bridge Records: 1866 (1 bridge report); County Administrative Records: Board of Supevisors Records: Road and Bridge, 1881 ( 1 drawing), 1883 (1 drawing and specifications); 1884 (1 diagram), 1885 (1 drawing), 1887 (1 drawing); Tax and Fiscal Records: 1863 (1 list for delinquent land tax), 1865 County Administrative Records: Commissioner of Revenue Record, 1907 (1 plat--delinquent lands sold), Lists of Delinquent Lands and Insolvent Capitation, 1867 (4 lists), 1868 (5 lists), 1869 (4 lists), County Administrative Records: Commissioner of Revenue Records, 1879 (2 sheets), County Adminstrative Records: Treasurer's Records 1887 (7 sheets), 1889 (1 document); Wills: 1874 (1 will and codicil), 1744-1911, Accession Number 41507.
- Records, 1735-1794, undated
  Wills: Partly Proven, 1735-1794 (broken series), 2 folders (Accession number 40724.) One folder of undated Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Court Records, Fiduciary Records, Justice of the Peace Records, Road and Bridge Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Accession number 41507.
- OVERSIZED Records, 1736-1840, undated
  Court Records: Petition of Separate Baptists to Amelia County Court Concerning a place in which to assemble and to Preach, 27 October 1768 (Negative photostat) (Accession number 22555); Election Records: Polls, 1752, 1755, 1761; Land Records: Plat of lots, undated, Survey Book, 1736-1751; Tax and Fiscal Records: Insolvent Lists, 1745, 1746, 1749, 1750, 1761; Individual lists of tithables (receipts), undated; Land and Personal property Tax Book, 1840 (Accession number 33213); Public Levy and County Accounts, 1743-1748, undated; List of taxable property, 1782; 1783 (2) 1784 (15); 1785 (4); 1786 (2) undated; County Adminstrative Records: Overseers of the Poor Records, Minutes and Orders, 1786-1787.
- Records, 1737-1907, undated
  Health and Medical Records: Lunacy Papers, 1795-1799, 1832-1833, 1835, 1844, 1859, 1895, 1902 and Smallpox Epidemic Papers, 1848, 1865; County Administrative Records: Overseers of the Poor Records, undated, 1737-1869(broken series); Public Buildings and Grounds Records, undated, 1786-1872(broken series); Court Records: Judgments, Arbitration Bond, 1749; Miscellanous Records, Conditional Sales(Personal Property), 1906-1907; Miscellaneous Records, Estray Books, 1774-1791; Estray Papers, undated, 1746-1860(broken series); Court Records, Judgments, Indemnifying Bonds, 1825, 1829, 1836, 1838, 1875, 1886; Miscellaneous Records, undated, 1755-1903(broken series); Papers of David Stokes, lawyer, 1785; Powers of Attorney, undated, 1794-1894(broken series.) Box also contains the following accessioned items: Health and Medical Records, Smallpox Epidemic Papers, 1837, County Adminstrative Records, Overseers of the Poor Bonds, 1814-1817; Proceedings of the Overseers of the Poor, 1816-1818; Statement of the Division of the Plate Money, 1860; Account of William Mann Late, Agent for Overseers of the Poor, 1834; Public Buildings and Grounds Records, Bill of Scantling for a Courthouse, 1792; Court Records: Judgments, Indemnifying Bonds, 1838, Miscellaneous Records: Documents found in bottom of box, undated; Epitaph found in Country Church Yard, undated; Sheet from Volume Containing Signatures, undated; Court Records: Clerk's Records, Memorandum of Contract, 1846; Contracts/Agreements Deposited With Clerk for Safe Keeping, 1850; Miscelleanous Records: Powers of Attorney, 1819; Tax and Fiscal Records: Tavern Book, ca. 1800--all with Accession numbers 37990, 37993, 37995 and Public Buildings and Grounds Records, Petitions to Move the Courthouse, undated, 1746--with Accession Number 37995. Also includes Plan of New Courthouse (1767) with Accession number 43189.